Hey בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is צ"ח Tzadi-Chet and
we pick up with the משנה Mishnah at the bottom of צ"ז
עמוד ב Tzadi-Zayin amud bet continuing with discussing when you sell things
and what happens if it doesn't turn out as what's expected or
there's some degree of contaminant and we now look at a case
which was quoted by a ברייתא Baraita related to in a ברייתא
Baraita earlier in the גמרא Gemara but here it is in the
משנה. Mishnah. המוכר יין לחברו והחמיץ, Hamocher yayin lachaveiro vehichmitzt, you sell
wine to your friend and then it sours, it becomes vinegar. אינו
חייב באחריותו, Eino chayav beachrayuto, that's not your responsibility. ואם ידוע שיינו
מחמיץ, Ve’im yadua sheyeino machmitz, but if it's known that your wine
has the propensity of turning vinegar, הרי זה מקח טעות. Harei zeh
mekach taut. So if it can be proven that this was
known
to be the case with your wine,
that this is a regular attribute of your wine, this buyer obviously
didn't know but you can then it's possible to bring evidence that
that actually has been the case and the pattern, then it is
a מקח טעות, mekach taut, then it and it is a nullified
sale. ואמר לו יין מבוסם אני מוכר לך, Ve’amar lo yayin mevusam
ani mocher lach, now if you tell him that very aromatic wine
I am selling you, so it was characterized as this particular way
and that presumably means something that will really have staying and lasting
power, then חייב להעמיד לו עד העצרת, Chayav le’amid lo ad ha’Atzeret,
then you have a responsibility if it sours
anytime prior to שבועות, Shavuot,
then
you the seller would have a responsibility to replace it. And the
רשב"ם Rashbam says but after עצרת Atzeret it's the summer and it's
very hot and then it's expected that the wine will sour. That's
no longer your responsibility. So if you characterize it that way, you
have a responsibility if it does not last until the summer.
וישן משל אשתקד, Veyashan mishel eshtakad, if you say it's old wine
then you have to sell it from at least last year's. OK.
ומיושן משל ג' שנים, U’meyushan mishel gimmel shanim, it is aged wine,
that would be different than old, then it is משל ג' שנים
mishel gimmel shanim three years, which the רשב"ם Rashbam says means counting
this year as one, so from two years ago. OK. Now it's
worth noting that in our משנה, Mishnah, right, it doesn't deal with
any of the issues we've been discussing prior in the גמרא, Gemara,
whether you sort of say that it's למקפה, lemikpeh, whether if it's
been specified that you're doing it to use for cooking wine and
therefore over a long period of time as opposed to using immediately,
if it is a question about like the first three days, the
last three days, those are issues that were discussed earlier in the
גמרא. Gemara. Here only a sparingly sort of makes reference to them
and the ראשונים Rishonim sort of try to fit it into some
of the principles before but we will just deal with this גמרא
Gemara as it takes this משנה Mishnah as it is and taking
it as it is it would seem that you know if you're
not saying that it's למקפה, lemikpeh, you're not saying that it's for
any prolonged period of time, then you can assume that maybe the
person will use it immediately and you have no responsibility. But again
it does not say under which rapidity did it begin to turn.
What if it turned even within three days? Anyway that is not
specified in the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara.
אמר רב יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rav Yose berabi Chanina, said רב
יוסי ברבי חנינא, Rav Yose berabi Chanina, לא שנו אלא בקנקנים דלוקח.
Lo shanu ela bekankanit deloke’ach. When is it true that the seller
has no responsibility if the wine sours? Only if it got transferred
to the לוקח's loke’ach vessels. אבל בקנקנים דמוכר, Aval bekankanit democher, but
if it was transferred but if you sold it in your vessels
and the guy took the wine with the vessels that you were
providing, so אמר
ליה החמר חבא קנקנך חבא, amar lei hachamar chava kankanach chava, then
the buyer can say back to him it's your wine, it's your
vessels and it soured, clearly this is all your responsibility. Wine is
not supposed to sour this quickly and it's a מקח טעות. mekach
taut. Now that sounds like it doesn't matter whether it sours immediately
or after a long time. If you take a look at the
רשב"ם Rashbam he says מצי אמר ליה לוקח אפילו זמן מרובה החמר
חבא קנקנך חבא. matzi amar lei loke’ach afilu zman merubeh hachamar chava
kankanach chava. OK, that it's definitely then still a מקח טעות. mekach
taut. But again that doesn't exactly fit with some of the discussion
earlier that it would only have to be within three days and
so on and the רשב"ם Rashbam tries to reconcile that with the
earlier גמרא. Gemara. OK, so let's take a look.
But now the גמרא Gemara says like this. OK. But that's at
least the way the גמרא Gemara here is saying it, that it's
only when it got transferred to the לוקח's loke’ach vessels but otherwise
the exact opposite of what the משנה Mishnah sounds, the seller actually
is responsible
without giving us a timeframe. OK.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: וכי קנקנים דמוכר מאי
הוי לימא ליה לא איבעי לך לשהוייה? Vechi kankanim democher mai havei
leima lei lo ibai lach lishahuye? So the גמרא Gemara says OK
but so what? The seller could say why was I assuming you
wanted the wine to store it for a long period? I assumed
you were going to drink it right away. So look, צריכא דאמר
ליה למקפי. tzricha d'amar lei l'mikphey. Now we're getting back to issues
we mentioned before that he said I want to use it for
cooking wine. Okay, so therefore if you say you want to use
it for cooking wine and the seller is selling it and it's
his vessels, then it's being sold with the understanding that it will
last for a while, not exactly clear how far a while is,
and if it turns sour before that time, it is a מקח
טעות mekach taut or it is the responsibility of the seller.
Okay. ומאי דוחקיה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא לאוקמי למתניתין בקנקנים דלוקח ודאמר
ליה למקפי. u'mai duchkei d'Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Chanina l'ukmei l'matnitin b'kankanim d'lokeach
v'd'amar lei l'mikphey. Now he's saying okay, I get that the rulings
all make sense, but why did you have to twist yourself in
interpreting the משנה Mishna this way? You assumed the case was that
it was specified for a long time and then you said that
the only reason the seller's off the hook is because it got
transferred to the vessels of the buyer. Why did you have to
twist yourself like that?
לוקמי בקנקנים דמוכר דלא אמר ליה למקפי. l'ukmei b'kankanim d'muchar d'lo amar
lei l'mikphey. Why not say that
nothing was specified for a long time and it was the seller's
vessels and without making any complicated situation in the משנה Mishna rather
than giving two criteria? You know you added two things to the
משנה. Mishna. You said a long time, but it was the buyer's
vessels. Why not just say you didn't say a long time, it
wasn't the buyer's vessels, and you're exempt because even though it was
the seller's vessels, you know the guy without specifying otherwise, you assume
the guy's gonna drink it right away. לוקמי בקנקנים דמוכר דלא אמר
ליה למקפי. l'ukmei b'kankanim d'muchar d'lo amar lei l'mikphey. אמר רבא Amar
Rava so רבא Rava said, מתניתין קשיא ליה. matnitin kashya lei. The
משנה Mishna bothered him. There was something about the משנה Mishna that
forced him to say that it was talking about למקפי, l'mikphey, that
the context was clear that it was a long time. Why? דקתני
אם ידוע שיינו מחמיץ הרי זה מקח טעות. d'tani im yadua sheyaino
machmitz harei zeh mekach taut. Because it says if it's known that
this person's wine has a propensity of souring, then of course it
would be no good. So then it would be a void sale.
So that bothered him. אמאי amai why is that true? If nothing
is specified of a long time, even in that case לימא ליה
לא איבעי לך לשהויי. lema lei lo ibai lach l'shahu'ei. You know,
you're buying wine, I'm not making promises for how long it'll last,
you shouldn't have had it sitting around, you should have drunk it
right away. So the idea that in the second case of the
משנה Mishna it's clearly a מקח טעות mekach taut if it's known
that it didn't have the ability to last a long time forces
us to say that the context of the משנה Mishna was one
where it was assumed that it was going to be needed to
last a long time. All right, so that makes sense. אמאי לימא
ליה לא איבעי לך לשהויי אלא לאו שמע מינה דאמר ליה למקפי
שמע מינה. amai lema lei lo ibai lach l'shahu'ei ela lav shma
mina d'amar lei l'mikphey shma mina. It must be that our משנה
Mishna is a context where it was assumed it was going to
last a long time and therefore if it has a propensity it's
a מקח טעות. mekach taut. But if that's the case, then the
only way the מוכר muchar the seller's off the hook is if
it got transferred to the vessels of the buyer because if it
was in the vessels of the seller and it was assumed for
a long time, then the seller actually would be responsible. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: דאמר ליה למקפי שמע
מינה ופליגי דרבי חייא בר יוסף. d'amar lei l'mikphey shma mina u'pligi
d'Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef. This argues on רב חייא בר יוסף Rav
Chiya bar Yosef that says that it is you know that only
if it basically what do you call it? Got transferred to the
vessels of the buyer. Argues on רב חייא בר יוסף. Rav Chiya
bar Yosef. דאמר רבי חייא בר יוסף חמרא מזלא דמרי גרים. d'amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef chamra mazla d'marei garim. When it comes to
wine, it is the מזל, mazel, the luck of the person who
currently owns it. Okay, so even if it was sold in the
vessels of the seller, once it got bad, it soured in the
possession of the buyer, we basically say that's the buyer's fault. Unless
there's something very concrete to hang it on the seller, like it
was known that the seller's wine soured. But otherwise, basically we say
that it was all because of the person
whose possession it is in. And we get this based on a
פסוק. pasuk. שנאמר ואף כי היין בוגד גבר יהיר. shene'emar v'af ki
hayayin boged gever yahir.
So the same way wine will rebel or betray and become vinegar,
how will that happen? That will happen to a person who you
know takes on airs that tries to represent himself as something he
is not. So it's like a מידה כנגד מידה. mida k'neged mida.
So this is interesting using like a theological idea, מזל, mazel, and
a פסוק pasuk like oh it's מידה כנגד מידה mida k'neged mida
to shift the responsibility. Okay, but according to that, he would say
the case of the משנה Mishna is even if it was assumed
to be a long time and even if it was the seller's
vessel, it's not the seller's responsibility. It happened to you, that's your
once you own the wine, that is your bad luck unless you
can specifically pin it on the seller because the seller is known
to sell bad wine. Okay. אמר רב מרי האי מאן דייהיר אפילו
אינש ביתיה לא מקבל. Amar Rav Mari hai man d'yahir afilu inish
beiteih lo mekabel. Somebody that takes on you know airs, often יוהרא
yuhra often like for religious airs, but you know basically is haughty
and presents themselves as something that they're not. he is intolerable even
to the members of his own household, which the רשב"ם Rashbam says
means his wife. Okay, so שנאמר shene'emar גבר יהיר ולא ינוה. Gever
yahir velo yinaveh.
A man who takes on airs and will not dwell. מאי לא
ינוה? Mai lo yinaveh? בנוה שלו, Benaveh shelo, even in his own
home he does
not—he can't be tolerated, especially because they can see through his, you
know, his hypocrisy. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav: כל המתגאה בטלית של תלמידי חכמים. Kol hamisga'eh betalis shel talmidei
chachamim. Now that we're talking about taking on airs and, you know,
appearances that you—that do not—that are not truthful, he says anybody
that boasts himself, you know, or lifts himself up through dressing like
a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and according, you know, there's ways the
גמרא Gemara sort of said that a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham has
his sort of garment in certain ways that are very clean and
so on. You know, nowadays you might say, depending on which culture
you're in, you know, you wear a black hat and a white
shirt and ציצית tzitzis out or whatever. Okay, but that's not representing
actually who you are.
So that's a very specific culture; I'm not saying those are the
only forms of תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Anyway,
ואינו תלמיד חכם, ve'eino talmid chacham, but you are not a Torah
sage, but you're dressing up as one and presenting yourself as one,
אין מכניסים אותו במחיצתו של הקדוש ברוך הוא. ein machnisin oso bimechitzaso
shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu. You are not—you know, when you die, you
will not be allowed to go into the boundary of God, you
know, within where God is present. כתיב הכא ולא ינוה, Kesiv hacha
velo yinaveh, and כתיב התם אל נווה קדשך, uchesiv hasam el neveh
kodshecha, to Your holy dwelling place.
So you do not get to enter into God's space because of
your—because you are presenting yourself as somebody you are not. Doesn't say
you have to be a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham to go into
God's space; just don't try to pretend you're somebody that you're not.
אמר רבא. Amar Rava.
Okay, now back to הלכה. halacha. האי מאן דזבין ליה חביתא דחמרא
לחנואה. Hai man dezavin lei chavisah dechamra lechanuva'ah. It says somebody who
sells a barrel of wine to a store owner, אדעתא לסבויי. ada'ata
le-savrei. So he does this with the intention that the store owner
will sell it over time.
ותקיף אפלגא או אתילתא, vesakif apalga o asilsa, and then the wine
becomes vinegar when it's only a half done or third done, דינא
הוא דמקבל ליה מיניה. dina hu demakabel lei minei. Then the guy
who sold it has to take it back and pay him for
the rest. Why? Because he basically, if you're selling it to the
store owner with the understanding that the store owner will sell it
little by little, that's sort of like the case of למקפי, lemikfe,
you know, and where you're implicitly assuring that it will last for
that period of time. And then if it soured, then you're liable
and you have to buy it back. Now the רשב"ם Rashbam actually
says that the case is that it's on consignment, that you're only
paying the store owner, he gets like a percentage of the profit,
but it's your wine. In that case, it's like obvious you have
to get it back; it's still your wine. תוספות Tosafot says that
the language דזבין, dezavin, sold, you know, makes it seem very clear
that it is, what do you call it, that it is actually
being sold. Okay, and nevertheless, you know, that it is still—it's sort
of like a case of למקפי, lemikfe, and because it's being sold
over time, then if it goes bad within the period of time
that you're implicitly promising that it will last for, then that's your
responsibility. ולא
אמרן אלא דלא שני בברזא. velo amaran ela dela shani beberza. Now
that's only true if the storekeeper did not change the spigot. Okay,
he did not do
something else that might have introduced the problem. אבל שני בברזא לא,
aval shani beberza lo, that if he changed the spigot, no. So
according to תוספות, Tosafot, it's just similar to the case like, you
know, like the קנקנין דלוקח, kankanin delokeiach, you did something now as
the buyer, so maybe it's your responsibility, maybe that's what made it
go bad. According to the רשב"ם, Rashbam, that it was never really
being sold, you would have to say that this is a case
of like פשיעה, peshia, of like negligence or something,
but תוספות's Tosafot's reading is clearly the simpler one: it was sold
and now don't blame me, you were the one who went ahead
and put on a new spigot. ולא אמרן אלא דלא מטא יומא
דשוקא. velo amaran ela dela mata yoma deshuka. And also that would
not only apply if it had not yet been the market time.
אבל מטא יומא דשוקא לא, aval mata yoma deshuka lo, but if
it had become like the market time, you know, then we would
not say it, because then in that type of a case, if
it was the market day, you could have sold all the wine,
and therefore if it didn't last beyond that day, that's no longer
my responsibility.
Okay. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava, and Rava also said: האי מאן דקביל
חמרא אדעתא דממטי ליה לפרוותא דזוט שפט. Hai man dekabbil chamra ada'ata
demamti lei lefarvasa de-Zut Shafat.
Somebody basically accepted wine on the understanding that they would bring it
to this place, פרוותא דזוט שפט, Parvasa de-Zut Shafat, name of a
place, you know, in and sell it there. So the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam explains this, this is a classic case of עיסקא, iska,
where you go ahead and, you know, I let's say I have—I
have money, I own the wine, and I—you're going to go ahead
and sell the wine, you'll get half the profits and take half
the losses, I'll get half the profits and half the losses. Okay,
and then that's a—could be a ריבית ribis problem, so I also
have to pay you for your efforts; we won't go into all
of that. Anyway,
and it's considered to be half of the wine... wine you are
borrowing from me, but it's now your wine, okay, so when I
lend you something like it's a, you know, I gave you the
wine, now you have to pay me back for it, but it's
your wine, that's why you get half the profits and half the
losses, and the other half of it is my wine and you're
just going ahead and selling my wine and I'm reaping the benefits,
okay, but I'll also reap I'll also take the losses. Now what
I tell you is that all of this deal only is you
can't sell it here because here the prices are low, and even
if the prices go up here, I'm insisting that you go to
this other town where you can get much higher prices for it.
Okay, so that was the arrangement. ועד מטי התם זל, V'ad mati
hasam zil,
and by the time the guy brought the wine there, the value
of wine went down. דינו הוא דמקבל ליה. Dinu hu de-mikabel leh.
The rule is, the law is, is that that's the responsibility, that
I, the person who gave you the wine but I imposed this
condition, I have to be the one that accepts all of that
loss because it was all because of the condition that I imposed,
and therefore I didn't even allow you, you know, to go ahead
with your own wine and sell it, and you could have, if
you had not had that restriction, you could have sold it here
and maybe made money. All right, so this is very complicated because
how does it exactly work out if it's half your wine and
half my wine, why am I able to impose the restriction, if
I do impose the restriction why does that make me liable? But
anyway, the basic idea is clear. I imposed the restriction so I
have to be responsible for the loss that occurs as a result.
Okay. איבעיא
להו, Ibaia lehu, they raise the following question. הוי חלא מאי? Havi
hala mai? Now in this case where I imposed the restriction, okay,
but it wasn't that the price went down and you could have,
you know, if you hadn't had that restriction you would have sold
it here, it was that by the time you got to this
place, it soured. What's the הלכה halacha there? So מאי? mai? אמר
ליה רב הילל
לרב אשי, Amar leh Rav Hillel le-Rav Ashi, כי הוינן בי רב
כהנא אמרי לן חלא לא. Ki havinan bei Rav Kahana amri lan
hala lo. When we were in the house of Rav Kahana, he
said no, חלא hala would be different. If it turned into wine,
that would be a different story. That's not my
even though I imposed the restriction, okay, even though I'm the one
that imposed the restriction and as a result it turned sour, that's
not all my responsibility. We're going to share in the responsibility, you
know, like any of the times of cases with this business deal,
we both equally suffer gain in the profits and suffer in the
losses. So even though I imposed this restriction, when wine goes bad,
that's not all on me, that's sort of on both of us,
okay? ודלא כרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, U-d'lo k'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina, and
it's not like Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina. What does this mean? Because
in our משנה, mishnah, the משנה mishnah was I sold wine and
it went bad and it was not my responsibility, okay, and so
you know and and we said that that was a case of
like למקפה, le-mikpeh, if you remember, which is that it was understood
that it was going to be for a long time and nevertheless
it wasn't the person who sold it's responsibility. So there's a parallel
here. Guy sells wine understood למקפה le-mikpeh and it's not his responsibility.
If it goes bad, the guy buys it. So I here, I'm
giving you this wine to sell, we're in business, I'm telling you
wait till you bring it to that place, that's sort of like
למקפה, le-mikpeh, it goes bad, don't come and blame me. That is
something that happened to the wine and we both suffer the loss,
you can't go ahead and put that on me. That is not
like Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina because Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina would say
actually in that case we can put it on you, and the
only reason in the משנה mishnah you're off the hook is because
it got transferred to the vessels of the buyer. But in that
type of a case actually if it went bad and it was
in the vessels of the seller, it would be the seller's responsibility.
And here too, because I the businessman am saying you have to
wait, it's sort of like למקפה, le-mikpeh, if it went bad and
it was in my vessels, that's all then on me, it's not
shared equally. ואיכא דאמרי אפילו חלא נמי מקבל, V'ika d'amri afilu hala
nami mikabel, and some say so that even if it does go
sour, even in the case of vinegar, that also is the responsibility
of the businessman. כמאן כרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, K'man k'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Chanina, like Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina because like who would say the
case of
the משנה mishnah actually it
is on the seller unless it got transferred to the vessels of
the buyer. And here too it's like למקפה le-mikpeh and it is
on the businessman and therefore you know
it is the responsibility of the businessman. It was his wine, he
he imposed the restriction, therefore he takes all the loss. It's not
like something external happened and that they both suffer the loss. Okay.
ישן משל אשתקד, Yashan mishel eshtakad, if you say it is going
to be you know old wine, it's last year's.
תנא ומישן והולך עד. Tana u'miyashen v'holech ad. and so on. Okay,
and if it goes bad before that time, you are responsible. משנה,
Mishnah, we are now done with the wine. Now we get into
a totally different discussion. Top of צ"ח עמוד ב. Tzadi Chet amud
bet.
המוכר מקום לחברו, Hamocher makom lechaveiro, if you sell a place to
your friend, like a plot of land, וכן המקבל מקום מחברו, vechein
hamikabel makom mechaveiro, or if you agree to, as we'll see, do
a construction for
somebody, לעשות לו בית חתנות לבנו בית אלמנות לבתו, laasot lo beis
chasnus livno beis almanus lebitto, to make a wedding home for like
a newlywed home, maybe is a better way to say it, for
your son, or a widow home for your daughter. So what does
that mean? Well first let's describe the case. Well is that you
know if people when their sons would get married they would move
in with their wives to their fathers, the son's father's home you
know but they would build like the you know the son's father
would build a like a wing or something or a little home
next to their home which would be for the newlywed couple. Okay,
so you went ahead and so it would usually be the groom's
father, we'll see why in the גמרא. Gemara. So you went ahead
and you said I would like to buy a plot of land
from you, you know, next to my land let's say you own
I don't know a whole you know major tract of land next
to my yard, I want to buy a space for you to
build my son's newlywed newlywed home for my son. And you say
great and we set a price. So the question is how big
of a space is it? I mean it's a little shocking to
think we would do that without specifying. Or I contract you and
say I'm going to hire you to build a newlywed's home and
we don't specify the amount. How big of a home do you
have to build? The other case is the widow's case. So if
the son and his wife are living with the groom's parents, then
the then my daughter, if it was a case of my daughter
getting married, she wouldn't be living on with me, she'd be living
with my husband's family. But if then her husband died, then she
would come back to live with me, but now she's already established
and she has kids or whatever, so she's not going to live
in my house, and I'll build her a separate house, my daughter,
I will build a widow's house for her if she's coming back
after widowhood to live with me. Those are the scenarios. So the
question is how big are these spaces, either for the contractor who's
building it, or when you are buying the plot of land? בונה
ארבע אמות על שש, Boneh arba amos al shesh, דברי רבי עקיבא.
divrei Rabi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva says it's a space, it's
a plot of land, or it's a building that's four אמות amos
by six. Six feet by eight. Pretty tiny. I don't know how
small like Manhattan apartments are but that's even smaller than that. רבי
ישמעאל אומר, רפת בקר היא זו. Rabbi Yishmael omer refes bakar hi
zo. No, he says that's like a stable, that is not a
place, that is not an acceptable minimal size for a newlywed's home.
Now, הרוצה לעשות רפת בקר בונה ארבע אמות על שש. harotzeh laasot
refes bakar boneh arba amos al shesh. And the next ruling is,
if in a similar way you decide to buy a plot of
land and said for a stable, or you contracted somebody to build
a stable, the dimensions are four אמות amos by six. We'll see
in the גמרא Gemara whether that's רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael saying it
or even רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva would concede that point. בית קטן,
Bayis katan, if you say if you contract somebody to build a
small house or you buy a plot of land for a small
house, that's שש על ח', shesh al ches, six אמות amos by
eight. Eight feet by what would that be, eight feet by twelve.
Okay, that's already a little bit maybe manageable,
assuming also the outhouses are outhouses. גדול, Gadol, if to build a
big house, ח' על עשר, ches al eser, eight אמות amos by
ten. טרקלין, Tarkalin, like a banquet hall, יוד על
יוד, yud al yud, ten אמות amos by ten, which is like
15 feet by 15 feet. רומו כחצי אורכו כחצי רחבו. Rumo kechatzi
orko kechatzi rachvo. The height of all of these houses would be
half of the combined width and length of the room. So if
the room was 8 by 10 feet, you add 8 plus 10,
18 feet, and it would have a 9-foot ceiling. If it was
12 by 12 feet, 24, then you would have a 12-foot ceiling.
Okay. ראיה לדבר, Raaya ladavar, so what would
be a proof, what's a source for this idea that this is
how high it has to be, right? And that would be pretty
high, you know, in our, you know, very, very high ceilings it
could be if it's a wide, if it's a big width and
length. ראיה לדבר, Raaya ladavar, רבי שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabi Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, כבניין היכל, kebinyan heichal, like the היכל heichal in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash that שלמה Shlomo built, it was, it
was 20 by 40 and the and the ceiling was 30 אמות.
amot. Okay, so which is half of 20 plus 40. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. למה לי למתני בית חתנות לבנו
בית אלמנות לבתו, Lama li lemisni beis chasnus livno beis almanus lebitto,
why is it giving specifically the scenarios that makes it clear that
the son who got married would live with his family and the
daughter would, you know, the daughter would live with the groom's family
and afterwards the daughter would come back to live with her if
there was a divorce or death would come back to live with
her family. ליתני בית חתנות לבנו ולבתו בית אלמנות לבנו ולבתו. Lisni
beit chasnut livno ulvitto beit almanut livno ulvitto.
Why couldn't it imagine like the reverse scenarios? מילתא אגב אורחיה קמשמע
לן Milta agav orchia kamashma lan this is teaching you something in
passing דלא דרכי דחתני למידר בי חמוה. Delo darkei dechasnei lemeidar bei
chamueh. Okay,
that a son-in-law should not live by his mother-in-law's home. Okay, that
the you basically the bride should move in with the groom and
not the groom moving in with the bride. Why? Because if the
groom moves in with the bride's family, then there's the mother-in-law and
that's seen as a sexual temptation. So okay. כדכתיב
בספר בן סירא Kidechsiv besefer Ben Sira like it's written in the
book of Ben Sira, interesting even though Ben Sira is one of
the ספרים חיצוניים, sefarim chitzoniyim, you know, the sort of apocryphal or
whatever the, you know, extra-canonical books and you're not supposed to read
it, the גמרא Gemara does sometimes quote it, okay, and this was
like a wisdom book. הכל שקלתי בכף מאזנים Hakol shakalti bechaf moznayim
I have weighed everything in the, you know, in the balance scales,
hold on. ולא מצאתי קל מסובין Velo matzasi kal misubin
I found nothing that is inferior than bran, like it's very light
and, you know, in terms of weight, but it's also like dross,
okay, that's like the most inferior thing is bran. וקל מסובין Vekal
misubin but even lighter, of less weight, of, you know, even more
inferior is חתן הדר בבית חמיו Chassan hadar beveit chamiv would be
a groom who lives in his in his mother-in-law's home. וקל מחתן
Vekal mechassan and even worse than that is אורח מכניס אורח Oreiach
machnis oreiach if a guest invites in another guest, like you're already
getting the hospitality of the homeowner and now you have the חוצפה
chutzpa to abuse that hospitality and invite in a guest on your
own accord. וקל מאורח Vekal me'oreiach and even worse than that is
משיב דבר בטרם ישמע Meshiv davar beterem yishma if you respond to
something before you fully have heard what the person was saying, I
think we're probably all a little guilty of that. שנאמר משיב דבר
בטרם ישמע אולת היא לו וכלימה Shene'emar meshiv davar beterem yishma ivvelet
hi lo uchelimma somebody
who responds to something before he hears it, it's a foolishness for
him and an embarrassment. Okay.
Now, let's take a look going on. רבי ישמעאל אומר Rabi Yishmael
omer, רפת בקר היא זו. refes bakar hi zo. הרוצה יעשה. Harotze
ya'aseh. רפת בקר מאן קתני לה? Refes bakar man katani lah? So
the גמרא Gemara asks after רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said back to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that doing something that small of four by
six is not a groom's home, but it is a or a
newlyweds' house, but it is a stable, who is then making the
next statement that a stable is the exact same dimensions, you know,
a four by six? מאן קתני לה? Man katani lah? איכא דאמרי
רבי ישמעאל קתני לה ואיכא דאמרי רבי עקיבא קתני לה. Ika de'amri
Rabbi Yishmael katani lah ve'ika de'amri Rabbi Akiva katani lah. You could
read the משנה Mishnah either way, either that it's a רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael statement or רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva statement. איכא דאמרי רבי
עקיבא קתני לה והכי קאמר. Ika de'amri Rabbi Akiva katani lah vehachi
ka'amar. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying and here's what he's saying:
אף על פי שרפת בקר היא. Af al pi sherefes bakar hi.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you're right, I know that it is
the size of a stable and I actually agree that a stable
is four by six, and nevertheless פעמים שאדם עושה דירתו כרפת בקר.
Pe'amim she'adam oseh diraso kirefes bakar.
People sometimes, you ever try to live in Manhattan? So people sometimes
will have a a house that's as small as a stable. So
you telling me it's the dimensions of a stable, that doesn't bother
me, I acknowledge that and nevertheless. ואיכא דאמרי רבי ישמעאל קתני לה
והכי קאמר. Ve'ika de'amri Rabbi Yishmael katani lah vehachi ka'amar. Or some
say that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is saying it and here's what
he's saying: כי שהרוצה לעשות רפת בקר עושה ארבע אמות על שש.
Ki sheharotze la'asos refes bakar oseh arba amos al shesh. רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael is saying, hey רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, four by six
is not a a proper size for a home, that is a
stable because a stable is four by six. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva might say, no, a stable is even smaller than four by
six and this is a stable, this isn't a home. Okay. טרקלין
עשר על עשר. Traklin eser al eser. A sort of a like
a banquet hall is ten by ten. מאי טרקלין? Mai traklin? קובסא
בי ורדי. Kuvsa bei vardi. Like a like a like
a booth or a hall with roses around it, something that's more
of a banquet hall rather than like a domicile because apparently domiciles,
you know, are more rectangular than square. תני וקנתיר Tani vekantir
if somebody says I'm going to build a קנתיר kantir twelve by
twelve. מאי קנתיר? Mai kantir?
תרביצא דפדני. Tarbitza depadni. What's a קנתיר? kantir? It is a type
of like a garden in front of a, you know, major building.
Okay. Like a courtyard of a mansion is how so that and
then again, that's a square size.
Okay. רומו כחצי אורכו וחצי רוחבו ראיה לדבר משכן ובית המקדש ובנין
היכל. Rumo kechatzi orcho vechatzi rochvo re'aya ladavar mishkan uveit hamikdash uvinyan
heichal. So okay, so now the height of the ceiling has to
be half of the combined width plus length. The proof to it,
רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel says oh that's like
the way they made the היכל. Heichal. ראיה לדבר מאן קתני לה?
Re'aya ladavar man katani lah? So the גמרא Gemara says it's a
funny grammar in the משנה. Mishnah. Who is saying ראיה לדבר? re'aya
ladavar?
Because it should have said רבי שמעון בן גמליאל אומר ראיה לדבר.
Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel omer re'aya ladavar. Who is saying ראיה לדבר?
Rayeh ledavar? Is it רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
or is it the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? איכא
דאמרי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל קתני לה. Ika de'amri Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel katni lah. Some say it is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel and that is probably the easiest way to read
the משנה. Mishnah. ראיה לדבר מנין? Rayeh ledavar minayin? What is the
proof? It is like setting it up for רבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. What is the proof to this? אמר רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל הכל כבנין היכל, Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hakol
kebinyan Heichal, like they did in the היכל Heichal where the height
of the ceiling is half of the combined width plus length. ואיכא
דאמרי תנא קמא קתני לה. V'ika de'amri Tanna Kamma katni lah. No,
here is a different way to read it. The תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma is saying ראיה לדבר, Rayeh ledavar, and there is a proof
to this idea that the ceiling, without saying what the proof is,
that the ceiling is half of the combined width plus length. ורבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אתמוהי קמתמה. V'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel atmohei kamisma. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is actually not supporting, but
he is sort of astounded and challenges. והכי קאמר ליה, V'hachi ka'amar
leih, this is what he says to the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma.
ראיה מנין? מבנין היכל? Rayeh minayin? Mibinyan Heichal? Where do you think
you want to prove this from? From the היכל? Heichal? אטו כל
עלמא כבנין היכל עבדי? Atu kol alma kebinyan Heichal avdi? What,
you think anybody's normal home is as grand as the היכל Heichal
in the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? What type of a proof is
that? So it is very nice, that is what the היכל'ס Heichal's
dimensions were. What does that show you about what the normal assumption
is for a home?
Okay. תניא, Tanya, we learned in a בריתא, Baraisa, חכמים אומרים רומו
כקורותיו. Chachamim omrim rumo kekorosav. That actually the height of a building
is like the beams of the roof. Now, the beams of the
roof were
put
parallel to the width of the
roof. They would run, you would put multiple beams on the top
of the walls, and they would run the length of the walls
and they would basically be equal to the width of the roof.
So actually, it is a way of saying that the height of
the ceiling has to be equal to the width. Not half of
the width plus the
length because that would make it even higher. But the width is
a smaller dimension, so the height of the ceiling has to be
based on the width of the roof. רומו כקורותיו. Rumo kekorosav. ולימא
רומו כרחבו? V'leima rumo kerachbo? So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but
if the beams are put parallel to the width, why not just
say the height of the ceiling is like the width? איבעית אימא
בסיסא מעילאי רווח. Ibayis eima basisa me'ilai revach.
For two reasons. One reason is that a house is wider at
the
top because they would build these things of stones.
So if you measure from wall to wall of the width, it
is longer at the top than at the bottom. Why? Because the
base is wider because it is of stones and you need that
to support the weight. So if you would have said the width,
then you might have measured the width at the bottom, at the
floor level, and that would have been shorter than the width measured
at the top when the walls get thinner. Okay, so a house
opens up at the top. ואיבעית אימא משום דאיכא בי כווי, V'ibayis
eima mishum de'ika bei kavei, because there is the places for the
holes for inserting the beams. The beams are not exactly the width.
The beams actually are longer than the width because they go into
holes in the wall. Okay, so it is actually a little bit
higher than the width,
a little bit longer than the width.
Okay. רב חנינא נפק לקרייתא. Rav Chanina nafik l'kiryasa. רב חנינא Rav
Chanina went out to the villages. רמי ליה קראי אהדדי. Remi leih
kra'i ahadadi. They asked him a contradiction of פסוקים. pesukim. כתיב, Ksiv,
it says, הבית אשר בנה המלך שלמה לה' ששים אמה ארכו ועשרים
רחבו ושלשים אמה קומתו, Habayis asher bana haMelech Shlomo l'Hashem shishim ama
orko v'esrim rachbo u'shloshim ama komaso, that the house, meaning the היכל,
Heichal, was sixty by twenty and thirty high. And that
is where we got our idea that it was half of the
combined width plus length. וכתיב, U'ksiv, but another verse says, ולפני הדביר.
V'lifnei haDvir. So that is the entire היכל, Heichal, which is the
קודש Kodesh and the קודש הקודשים. Kodesh HaKodashim. But the דביר, Dvir,
the קודש הקודשים, Kodesh HaKodashim, was twenty by twenty. So
the outside part was forty by twenty, the קודש הקודשים Kodesh HaKodashim
was twenty by twenty, the entire thing was sixty by twenty.
Okay. ולפני הדביר עשרים אמה אורך ועשרים אמה רוחב ועשרים אמה קומתו.
V'lifnei haDvir esrim ama orech v'esrim ama rochav v'esrim ama komaso. Ah,
but then it says it was only twenty high. So when you
are describing it all, you are saying sixty by twenty by thirty.
But when you are describing just the קודש הקודשים Kodesh HaKodashim part,
you are saying twenty by twenty by twenty. It should have been
twenty by twenty by thirty. So, אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said back to them, כי קחשיב משפת כרובים ולמעלה. Ki kachashiv
misfas kruvim u'lemala. No, no, no. When it is measuring the twenty,
it is not measuring the entire height from the floor to the
ceiling in the קודש הקודשים. Kodesh HaKodashim. It is measuring from the
top of the כרובים. kruvim. And it says שלמה Shlomo built these
two gold כרובים kruvim standing on the ground that were ten אמות
amos high. So from the top of the כרובים kruvim to the
ceiling is twenty. Now, why should it measure that way as opposed
to measuring from the floor to the ceiling? מאי קא משמע לן?
Mai ka mashma lan? What is this teaching you? Top of דף
צ"ח עמוד א'. Daf tzadi ches amud alef. הא קא משמע לן
למטה כלמעלה, Ha ka mashma lan lemata k'lemala,
that the bottom ten is just like the top twenty above the
כרובים. kruvim. מה למעלה אין משמש כלום אף למטה אין משמש כלום.
Ma lemala ein mshamesh klum af lemata ein mshamesh klum. Just as
the top twenty is totally empty, even
below it is totally empty. Even though below in the bottom ten
height there's the כרובים *keruvim* and the ארון *aron*, in a magical
way they don't actually take up any space. Okay, and we will
continue with that point tomorrow.